{"tossups": [{"question": "In this city, Roland Freiser presided over the extra-judicial People\u2019s Court. The communist Marinus van der Lubbe was convicted of arson in this city in 1933. This city\u2019s Gauleiter for two decades was Joseph Goebbels, and a famous photo taken by Yevgeny Khaldei shows a soldier raising a Soviet flag over this city\u2019s Reichstag. The F\u00a8uhrerbunker was constructed in, for ten points, what capital city of Nazi Germany?", "answer": "<b> Berlin</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Billy Mitchell tirelessly promoted the use of these objects in warfare following his dismissal from the military. Traveling performers who made use of these objects in the 1920s became known as barnstormers. A wooden one of these objects nicknamed the Spruce Goose was designed by Howard Hughes. Two siblings worked in a bicycle shop to build one of these objects that they operated in Kitty Hawk in 1903. For ten points, name these vehicles that were first piloted by the Wright Brothers.", "answer": "air<b>plane</b>s (accept<b> aircraft</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A scandal in this country involved the changing of Ewha University\u2019s standards to allow for nepotism. A leader of this country allegedly drew upon a shadow cabal of advisers known as the \u201cEight Heavenly Fairies.\u201d An investigation in this country revealed that many presidential speeches had been altered ahead of time by the shaman Choi Soon-Sil. For ten points, name this country whose president Park Geun-Hye was impeached in 2017 in the midst of mass protests in Seoul.", "answer": "<b> South Korea</b> (or the<b> Republic of Korea</b>; do not accept Democratic People\u2019s Republic of Korea)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "An ancient Egyptian version of this instrument was called the sheneb, and the salpinx was a version used by ancient Greek soldiers. Anton Weidinger played a keyed version of this instrument, and Jeremiah Clarke\u2019s<em> Prince of Denmark\u2019s March</em> is known as its \u201cVoluntary.\u201d This instrument has a cylindrical bore, unlike the cornet, and is twice as long as a related instrument used to play \u201cTaps,\u201d the bugle. For ten points, name this highest-pitched brass instrument in a standard orchestra.", "answer": "<b> trumpet</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this city where Dolley Madison saved paintings that were hung in the White House.", "answer": "<b> Washington</b>, D.C. (or the<b> District of Columbia</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One leader of this empire passed the Ecloga law code and ruled after the 20 Years Anarchy. A leader of this empire won the Battle of Kleidion and married his sister Anna to Vladimir the Great of Kiev. Tribonian composed a law code of this empire named for a leader who faced the Nika Riots. Basil II the Bulgar Slayer ruled this empire, which was founded by Constantine I. For ten points, name this empire, ruled by Justinian the Great from Constantinople, that fell in 1453.", "answer": "<b> Byzantine</b> Empire (accept<b> Eastern Roman</b> Empire; do not prompt on Rome or Roman Empire alone)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 1962, this Prime Minister\u2019s country lost the Aksai Chin region to China after a brief border war. After this man\u2019s mentor was assassinated, this man gave an impromptu speech in which he said \u201cthe light has gone out of our lives.\u201d On the eve of his nation\u2019s independence, this leader described his people\u2019s\u201ctryst with destiny.\u201d For ten points, name this prot\u00b4eg\u00b4e of Mahatma Gandhi and opponent of Muhammad Ali Jinnah, the first and longest-serving Prime Minister of India.", "answer": "Jawaharlal<b> Nehru</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This river became the site of Fort Brown after a military buildup by Zachary Taylor, whose men were ambushed near this river in the Thornton Affair. A dispute over the deaths of federal troops during the\u201cSpot Resolutions\u201d was prompted by the United States\u2019 use of this river, not the Nueces, as a southern boundary; that territorial dispute prompted President Polk to begin the Mexican-American War. For ten points, name this river that forms the south Texan border.", "answer": "Rio<b> Grande</b> (or Rio<b> Bravo</b> del Norte)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A prelude to one of these wars was an attempt to kidnap the king known as the Amboise [am-bwahz] Conspiracy. During these wars, the Massacre of Vassy was orchestrated by the Duke of Guise [gheez]. One army in these wars was commanded by the prince of Cond\u00b4e and Gaspard de Coligny [co-lih-nee]. The phrase \u201cParis is well worth a Mass\u201d was spoken by Henry IV, who ended the last of these wars by issuing the Edict of Nantes, promising toleration. For ten points, name this set of 16th century wars between Protestant Huguenots and Catholics in a certain country.", "answer": "<b> French</b> Wars of<b> Religion</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The Battle of Yellow Tavern was a decisive clash between two units of this type. At the start of the Overland Campaign, Philip Sheridan was recalled from the west to lead a unit of this type. A commander of this type of unit, John Buford, established the Union defensive lines at the Battle of Gettysburg. J.E.B. Stuart led a Confederate unit of this type, which were often used in the Civil War for raiding and reconnaissance. For ten points, give this term for units of mounted troops.", "answer": "<b> cavalry</b> (accept<b> mounted</b> units before read; accept<b> horse</b>men or similar answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This city hosted the only Olympic performance of Eddie \u201cThe Eagle\u201d Edwards, a British ski jumper whose performance was bad enough that the Olympics instituted stricter qualification rules. The first Olympic performance of the Jamaican bobsled team came in this city, whose Olympic Saddledome and Stampede Corral were used as venues for its 1988 Winter Olympics. For ten points, name this Canadian city whose NHL team, the Flames, competes with the Edmonton Oilers for bragging rights in Alberta.", "answer": "<b> Calgary</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "This man was wounded and captured at the Battle of Aspromonte, after which he retired to Caprera. During the Franco-Prussian War, this general led the Army of the Vosges. After a handshake at Teano, this leader declared his loyalty to King Victor Emanuel II. This ex-member of the Carbonari led his redshirts on the Expedition of the Thousand to conquer the Kingdom of Two Sicilies. For ten points, name this general who led the military campaigns that unified Italy.", "answer": "Giuseppe<b> Garibaldi</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>The winning side of this war controversially suffered non-battle casualties when Nelson</b> <b>Miles\u2019 soldiers ate spoiled \u201cembalmed beef.\u201d The telegraphed instruction (+)</b> <b>\u201cfurnish the</b> <b>\u201cfurnish the</b> <b>pictures and I\u2019ll furnish the war\u201d allegedly helped prompt this conflict, as the (*)</b> <b>pictures and I\u2019ll furnish the war\u201d allegedly helped prompt this conflict, as the (*)</b> yellow journalism of William Randolph Hearst raised tensions after the sinking of the USS<em> Maine</em>. Puerto Rico and Guam were ceded to the United States following, for ten points, what 1898 war against a European power that had controlled Cuba?", "answer": "<b> Spanish-American</b> War", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This student of Lentulus Batiatus lends his name to a 20th-century league co-founded by Karl Liebknecht. One subordinate of this man faced a major setback after being defeated by Publicola near Mount Garganus; that man, (+) Crixus was killed along with another of this man\u2019s allies, Oenomaus. This man was finally defeated at the Battle of Siler River, and after his death, many of his (*)</b> followers were crucified along the Appian Way. For ten points, name this former gladiator who led a slave revolt against the Roman Republic.", "answer": "<b> Spartacus</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>Description acceptable. Rupert Vance\u2019s 1932 work about</b><em><b> The Human Geography of</b></em><b> this location responded to a manifesto from defenders of this region titled</b><em><b> I\u2019ll Take My Stand</b></em><b>. John Crowe Ransom led a defense of this area against works like H.L. Mencken\u2019s \u201cSahara</b> <b>of the Bozart,\u201d which lampooned this region\u2019s alleged (+)</b> <b>intellectual backwardness. Like</b> <b>Harlem, this region enjoyed a literary \u201cRenaissance,\u201d including authors like Robert Penn Warren and (*) </b> William Faulkner. For ten points, name this broad geographic area that underwent Reconstruction after the Civil War.", "answer": "the American<b> South</b> (\u201dthe South\u201d completes the title of the Vance work, but accept other answers like the<b> Deep South</b>,<b> Dixie</b>land, the<b> former Confederacy</b>; do not accept \u201cthe Confederacy,\u201das all early clues are post-Civil War)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b>This leader\u2019s administration included Marc Lalonde\u2019s highly unpopular National Energy Program. As Prime Minister, this man agreed to Roy McMurtry, Roy Romanow, and Jean Chretien\u2019s so-called \u201cKitchen Accord;\u201d that agreement led to this man signing an 1982</b> <b>act (+)</b> <b>patriating his country\u2019s constitution and granting his country sovereignty. This</b> <b>supporter of bilingualism cracked down on the (*)</b> FLQ during the 1970 October Crisis. For ten points, name this two-time Liberal Prime Minister of Canada and father of Canada\u2019s current PM, Justin.", "answer": "<b> P</b>ierre<b> Trudeau</b> (accept Joseph Philippe<b> P</b>ierre Yves Elliott<b> Trudeau</b>; prompt on Trudeau)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Because of her connections to this person, boarding house owner Mary Surratt became the first woman to be executed by the U.S. government. This man was treated for a broken</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>leg by Samuel Mudd before dying in a shootout with federal troops on a farm in</b> <b>northern Virginia. This man\u2019s reputation as an (*)</b> actor allowed him to sneak into a performance at Ford\u2019s Theatre, where he jumped onto the stage and shouted \u201cSic Semper Tyrannis\u201d after shooting a U.S. president. For ten points, name this assassin of Abraham Lincoln.", "answer": "John Wilkes<b> Booth</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}